Preliminary Guide to the Richard Bausch Papers, 1965-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard Bausch papers 1965-1998 and undated
Bausch, Richard, 1945-
13.5 linear feet Extent: 1600 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00093
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Collection also contains sensitive information. Patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Richard Bausch Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1998.
Biographical Note
1945 Born, Fort Benning, Georgia
1974 B.A., George Mason University
1975 M.F.A., University of Iowa
1980 Real Presence
1980- Professor of English and creative writing, George Mason University
1981 Take Me Back
1982 National Endowment for the Arts grant
1984 The Last Good Time Guggenheim Fellowship
1987 Spirits and Other Stories
1989 Mr. Field's Daughter
1990 The Fireman's Wife and Other Stories
1992 Violence
1993 Rebel Powers
1994 Rare and Endangered Species: A Novella and Stories
1995 Aren't You Happy for Me? and Other Stories
1996 Good Evening Mr. and Mrs. America, and All the Ships at Sea: A Novel The Selected Stories of Richard Bausch
1998 In the Night Season
1999 Someone to Watch Over Me: Stories
2002 Hello to the Cannibals
Collection Overview
The Richard Bausch Papers, 1965-1998, document the career of the American novelist and short story writer through personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, and printed materials. The Correspondence Series begins in the 1960s with mainly personal letters, but by the 1970s begins to document Bausch's emergent writing career, including mention of his work on early short stories and his acceptance to the Iowa Writers' Workshop. From that point on several prominent American writers and literary figures appear, including frequent correspondence at various times with Charles Baxter, Frederick Busch, Richard Ford, George Garrett, Gordon Lish, William Maxwell, and C.K. Williams; Bausch's agent, Harriet Wasserman; and his twin brother, novelist Robert Bausch. Prominent though less frequent correspondents include Fred Chappell, Alan Gurganus, Barry Hannah, and Jean Thompson. The Writings Series documents the development of Bausch's novels and story collections and consists mainly of typescripts and various stages of proofs. Although most are fair copies or only moderately hand-corrected, the sheer number of versions documents the process of creation. Of special note in this regard are the novels Rebel Powers and Violence. Two smaller series, Printed Materials and Writings by Others, make up the remainder of the collection. Highlights of the latter series include a copy of Bob Balaban's screenplay for the Bausch novel, The Last Good Time, and typescripts of several early stories by Gurganus dating from the 1970s.
Subject Headings
Bausch, Richard, 1945-; Balaban, Bob; Bausch, Robert, 1945-; Baxter, Charles, 1947-; Busch, Frederick, 1941-; Chappell, Fred, 1936-; Ford, Richard, 1944-; Garrett, George P., 1929-; Lish, Gordon; Maxwell, William, 1908-; Wasserman, Harriet; Williams, C. K., (Charles Kenneth), 1936-; Iowa Writers' Workshop; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; American literature -- 20th century; American literature -- Southern States; Short stories; Southern literature
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1965-1998
  Professional and personal correspondence and printouts of e-mail, arranged in chronological incoming and outgoing sequences.
  This series is restricted. Richard Bausch's written consent is required prior to access. Contact Research Services.
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1965-1998, (13 folders) (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1989-1998, (5 folders) (Box 2)
- Writings Series, 1975-1996 and undated
  Arranged alphabetically by book title. Folders for single stories are filed after the book titles in a separate alphabetical sequence. Writings in other genres, including poetry, and miscellaneous fragments of fiction manuscripts appear at the end of the series. A number of the typescripts were printed out from diskettes included in the collection; these are marked with a "Disk" number in the upper left hand corner of the first page.
  - A Domestic Education, (unpublished novel), 1977 (Box 2)
  - A Former Catholic, (Master's Thesis, University of Iowa) 1975, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Good Evening Mr. and Mrs. America, and All the Ships at Sea, 1996 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - In the Night Season, 1997 and undated, (Folder 1 of 6) (Box 2)
  - In the Night Season, 1997 and undated, (Folders 2-6 of 6) (Box 3)
  - The Last Good Time, 1984 and undated, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - The Last Good Time,(play), undated (Box 3)
  - Mattie, (unpublished novel), undated (Box 3)
  - Mr. Field's Daughter, 1986-1989 and undated, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Plains, 1991-1992. See also Rebel Powers., (Folders 1-12 of 15) (Box 4)
  - Plains, 1991-1992, (Folders 13-15 of 15) (Box 5)
  - Rare & Endangered Species, 1992-1994, (11 folders) (Box 5)
  - Real Presence, 1978-1979, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Rebel Powers, 1989-1992 and undated See also Plains., (Folder 1 of 12) (Box 5)
  - Rebel Powers, 1989-1992 and undated, (Folders 2-12 of 12) (Box 6)
  - The Singers, (unpublished, unfinished novel), undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Spirits and Other Stories 1986 and undated, (Folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 6)
  - Spirits and Other Stories, 1986 and undated, (Folder 4 of 4) (Box 7)
  - Spirits, (unpublished novel), 1981-1983 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - The Summer Before the Wars, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Take Me Back, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Violence, 1986-1992, (8 folders) (Box 7)
  - Winter Houses, (unpublished novel), undated (Box 7)
  - Short stories, 1970-1993 and undated, (62 folders) (Box 8)
  - Poetry, 1967-1997 and undated, bulk 1969-1979, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Fiction, Fragments, and Notes, 1975-1993, bulk undated, (13 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1973-1987, bulk undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Files, 1975-1995 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 9)
- Printed Materials Series, 1971-1993 and undated
  Printed materials by and about Bausch. Includes some early stories in journals, clippings, reviews, publicity material, and miscellaneous other printed items. Arrangement parallels the general structure of the Writings Series: fiction first, followed by writings in other genres and ending with miscellaneous materials about Bausch and other topics.
  - Writings, 1971-1991, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Clippings and Reviews by Bausch, 1988-1989, 1992, 1995 (Box 10)
  - Clippings and Reviews about Bausch, 1984-1993, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1979-1993 and undated (Box 10)
- Writings By Others Series, 1972-1995 and undated
  Typescripts and printed material by various authors, most of it inscribed to Bausch by the authors. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Balaban, Bob (Box 10)
    - Last Good Time (screenplay), 1990 (Box 10)
  - Bausch, Robert
    - Dog-Star, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Stag Party, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Suicide Note, 1977 (Box 10)
  - Berg, Elizabeth
    - The No More Baby Blues, undated (Box 10)
  - Chibka, Robert
    - Inventory, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Everhard, Jim
    - Through the Eye of a Needle, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Ford, Richard
    - Jealous, undated (Box 10)
    - The Womanizer, undated (Box 10)
  - Garrett, George
    - The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - The Tyranny of Sloth, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Gurganus, Allan
    - The Expense of Spirit, 1974 (Box 10)
    - First Stories (master’s thesis), 1975 (Box 10)
    - Minor Complications, 1975 (Box 10)
  - McCann, Richard, poetry, undated (Box 10)
  - O'Brien, Tim
    - Loon Point, undated (Box 10)
  - Stafford, Jean, various short stories, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry, undated (Box 10)
  - Unknown
    - Perspiration, undated (Box 10)
Materials Cataloged Separately
The following twelve books by Bausch were removed from the collection (accession 1998-0555) and cataloged separately.
The Fireman's Wife and Other Stories, New York: Simon and Schuster, c1990.
Good Evening Mr. & Mrs. America, and All the Ships at Sea, New York: HarperCollinsPublishers, c1996.
In the Night Season, New York: HarperFlamingo, c1998.
The Last Good Time, New York: Vintage Books, 1994.
Mr. Field's Daughter, New York: Linden Press, 1989.
Rare & Endangered Species, Boston: Houghton Mifflin/Seymour Lawrence, 1994.
Real Presence, New York: Dial Press, c1980.
Rebel Powers, Boston: Houghton Mifflin/Seymour Lawrence, 1993.
The Selected Stories of Richard Bausch, New York: Modern Library, 1996.
Spirits and Other Stories, New York: Linden Press/Simon & Schuster, 1987. Signed and inscribed by the author.
Take Me Back, New York: Dial Press, c1981.
Violence, Boston: Houghton Mifflin/Seymour Lawrence, 1992.
Related Material
The following collection in the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library may contain related material:
Robert Bausch Papers, ca. 1968-1999